this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at SC - radio dotnet SC radio is
brought to you by the I Triple E
Computer Society I Triple E software
magazine online at computer org slash
software digital ocean is the easiest
cloud platform to deploy manage and
scale applications of any size removing
infrastructure friction and providing
predictability so developers and their
teams can deploy faster and focus on
building software the customers love
digitalocean stands out from the crowd
due to its simplicity high performance
and no billing surprises join a
community of over 3.5 million developers
on digital ocean sign up with a free
credit at doco / SC radio for software
engineering radio this is Robert bloomin
today I have with me Chris Richardson
Chris is an experienced software
architect and consultant active in the
field of micro services his startup
eventuate IO provides a platform for the
development of transactional micro
services Chris is the publisher of the
website microservices dot IO and the
author of the recently published book
micro service patterns which we will be
talking about today Chris welcome to
software engineering radio oh thanks
pleased to be yeah Chris would you like
to tell the listeners anything about
yourself that I didn't cover in the bio
well I think he just about covered it I
mean I these days I as well as working
on my startup I basically travel the
world helping clients adult micro
services through a combination of
consulting and training let's get on to
micro service patterns we have done a
number of other shows on micro services
including number two 13 to 10 on
architecture and micro services and 351
on orchestrating micro services so we're
not going to
do an in-depth review but tell the
listeners what does Microsoft wear
technology or the ability to deliver
software rapidly frequently and reliably
is becoming essential to most if not all
organizations right you know the whole
concept of software is eating the world
and so in order to deliver software
rapidly frequently and reliably you need
a combination of should we say three
things first is you need to embrace
DevOps write a set of practices
essentially a software development
methodology you need to structure your
engineering organization into small
autonomous teams so-called - pizza teams
although that's somewhat of a imprecise
metric and then lastly you need an
architecture that supports all of this
and on the one hand if you're building
relatively small applications you can
probably get away with using the
monolithic architecture but if you're if
you've got a large number of developers
and you're building a large complex
application chances are you actually
need to use the microservice
architecture and essentially the micro
service architecture breaks up what
would otherwise be a monolith into a set
of relatively small but not tiny
services that can individually be
developed and tested and deployed and
scaled by by the team that owns them I
want to move on now and talk about
design patterns or microservice patterns
when the book design patterns came out
some 20 years ago I believe the authors
did not see themselves as really
originating these ideas they were more
documenting solutions to problems that
had been discovered and proven
themselves over time with your work on
microservice patterns was your
assessment
of the state of the community in terms
of adoption is there an agreed upon set
of best practices or is this more your
view of how things should be done I
would say my book is kind of a
combination of both I mean you're right
I mean in many ways there's no such
thing as a a new pattern you know it's
really a kind of essentially a labeling
and a more formal description of
something that has existed within
whatever field you're studying for some
period of time and it has demonstrated
itself to be generally useful so sort of
you know so a lot of identifying
patterns is really just mining what
people are doing perhaps in some cases
giving them a name and then kind of
trying to distill down a description of
the solution but then also describe the
benefits and the drawbacks of that
particular approach so it's sort of a
way of structuring something that has
existed out there already would be fair
to say then these patterns become a
toolbox for architects to build their
own micro service based architecture
yeah I think that's a good way of
thinking about it I mean why don't one
of sort of one of the key ideas with
patterns in general and Satan and sort
of my book in particular is that when
you apply a pattern right and that
pattern you know the definition of a
pattern is a reusable solution to a
problem you apply a pattern that
actually solves some problem you know in
the case of the micro-service
architecture the problem you're trying
to solve is how do i structure my
application in a way that requires rapid
reliable and frequent delivery of
software
but at the same time that actually it
invariably creates subproblems for
instance you know with a microservice
architecture it one obvious sub-problem
is well how do you break up your system
into a set of services and then there's
also a whole bunch of patterns related
to why you're now building a distributed
system and so there's some various
problems around that and so essentially
you you apply one pattern that creates
subproblems which you then apply other
patterns to solve and effectively you'll
sort of you know you're doing that
recursively so to speak and so these
patterns form a web of interrelated
patterns and so when you are creating an
architecture you're essentially
traversing this graph selecting patterns
and then selecting patterns to the
subproblems and so on and so forth so it
actually kind of provides a structure to
this problem space and tells architects
what problems they they're gonna think
they're going to encounter but there and
then also how to solve them given that
the design patterns they are the
solution to a problem what are some of
the problems posed by micro services
that you don't have with the monolith
that require a new and different set of
patterns to solve yeah so first problem
is what services am I gonna have you
know it's like that's the key question
you know it's not oh you know which
deployment technology are we gonna have
should we use server list versus dock or
anything like that
in reality a lot of those technical
issues that people tend to focus on a
much more like a detail so number one is
what services are you gonna have and
then once and they have some patterns
for the
and then once you've you've come up with
a set of services it's like oh well one
of the key on one key aspect of the
micro service architecture is that each
services data is encapsulated within
that service and that immediately
creates two subproblems
how do you implement transactions that
span services and then how you how do
you implement queries that span services
and and so that then leads to the saga
pattern which is a way of managing
transactions and then there's a couple
of querying patterns API composition and
CQRS
that solve the querying part of it so
that's sort of like you know there's
sort of if you think of it as ending
well it's kind of a graph or a tree yeah
that's one major sort of sub branch that
you have pattern solution problem
solution pairs that you end up going
down summarize you're drawing attention
to going from a centralized data to
distribute a data possibly multiple data
stores as introducing a whole set of
problems that the architect has to solve
is is that correct yeah yeah okay great
just wanted to summarize that I would
say a point of clarification is on the
one hand services might actually have in
a in a very literal sense their own
database server but quite often all you
need is sort of a kind of a logical
separation of data so like you could
have a shared relational database server
and then with on that server each
service can have its own database schema
so logical division now obviously it all
depends on the scale and the scale and
complexity of your application but I
don't want anyone who's listening to go
oh my god I have to buy 10 X as many
name your database Ven
licenses in order to do micro services
what I think you're talking about is in
a monolithic application there could be
one single schema if it's a relational
database I'm free to write a query that
joins the user table to the orders table
to the product table to the product
description table there's no limit on
how big of a sequel joint I can write as
long as it will run but in the Micra
service is a minimum you might have user
orders product and they're a micro
service and they might still all be on
the same server but you're not going to
allow sequel to join across those
boundaries because there are a minimum
it's a logical boundary is that where
you're going with that point yeah that's
exactly right the the tables of a
service are essentially equivalent to
the private fields of a class they are
it's part of its implementation and they
are hidden from the outside world and
they're only accessible indirectly
through that services API great so we've
been talking about a set of problems
that are caused by going for more of a
distributed or partitioned data model I
believe you had another set of problems
in your graph of of problems that you
are going to highlight that that are
specific to the micro service
architecture oh yeah
so another sort of class of technical
problems well I've got a bunch of
services and how and then how do they
communicate now on the one hand into
process communication is is sort of
happens in a monolithic system because a
monolithic application has to
communicate with other applications but
I would argue that the sort of the
degree of complexity around that is
significantly higher in a in a micro
service architecture because the part
the services that make up the apple
Kayson are having to communicate with
one another so it's sort of inter
process communication is much more
central to your application architecture
and so there there's this sort of
pattern basic patterns like should you
use asynchronous messaging versus
synchronous communication mechanisms
such as rest or G RPC so that's that's
sort of one sort of sub problem that you
have to address let's move on to talking
about what some of the patterns are and
since we're talking about communication
you do introduce these different
families of communication patterns
between microservices synchronous and
asynchronous breakdown when do you
choose one when do you choose the other
and what are the strengths and
weaknesses yeah so on the one hand let's
just say using rest is in a sense the
de-facto communication mechanism right
yeah Jason well to be more precise Jason
over HTTP you know that's super familiar
everyone you know it obviously works
with browsers but then it's just super
familiar so up but on the one so on the
one hand that it's kind of simple to use
but on the other hand that actually
introduces Tyco runtime coupling between
the services you know sir if say the
order service implements a REST API and
then it while handling one of those
requests it has to make a synchronous
cooled or the customer service and wait
for a response to come back then in that
situation the there's temporal coupling
between the two the order service can't
send back a response unless the customer
service that can send back a response
and suddenly the availability of that
endpoint is you know the availability of
one service to the power two and if you
end up with more complex architectures
and more complex patterns of interaction
the availability of your system overview
API starts to drop off dramatically and
so for those reasons that it's it's
actually preferable to rely on
asynchronous communication as much as
possible and in fact a common
anti-pattern is to go well we're just
gonna break our system up into a bunch
of services and they're gonna
communicate using HTTP right or rest and
you know there you've basically built a
system that's tightly coupled at runtime
with multiple points of failure in your
book in your book you introduce a
recurring example of the food to go
software-as-a-service could you briefly
describe that example and talk about a
couple of points in food to go that
would use synchronous and another one or
two that would use asynchronous and why
you choose one or the other oh yeah so
it's an online food delivery application
you know along the lines of uber eat
sword or Daschle deliver room and you
know my first book pojos in action which
came out 13 years ago had the same
example but it was it was a monolith so
the scenario envisaged in Mike receivers
is patterns is well ten plus years have
gone by and and the in the food to go
application has outgrown its monstrous
kind of it now has a monstrous monolith
and is having problems delivering
software rapidly I'm sure we can all
relate to that yeah it's it's a
incredibly common scenario right so so
so in the case of the microservice
version of that application we take a
request like placing an order several
things have to happen when an order is
placed you have to do some validation
around can the consumer place orders is
the order valid from the restaurants
perspective is the restaurants kitchen
willing to
accept orders at this time and then you
also have to charge the consumers credit
card as well so in the monolithic
application conceptually all those
happen with inside the monolith but in
the micro service architecture the order
service ends up collaborating
asynchronously with numerous services
such as the consumer service the kitchen
service and the accounting service and
it's also subscribing to a stream of
events that are coming out of the
restaurant service so that it has a
replica of the restaurants data in its
own database so it doesn't actually have
to interact with the restaurant service
I'm gonna not go through every single
one of those but I'm gonna pick one why
would the collaboration with the
accounting service be asynchronous well
one way to think about it is sort of the
model is so there's a rest date so the
order service has a REST API to create
an order that API actually returns
immediately saying essentially saying
the request to create this order has
been received check back later to see
what the status of it is and all of the
processing required to basically fight
will validate and finalize that order
happens asynchronously and including
charging the consumers credit card now
in the normal case that everything
should happen within let's just say tens
of milliseconds or something like that
so from the users perspective the order
could actually be processed
instantaneously but the nice thing is is
why one part of the system is
temporarily down orders will still be
accepted just that the processing of
them might be delayed briefly what
you're driving at then is the decisions
you make about what's synchronous and
what's asynchronous will have an impact
on the availability of the system its
ability to do or
can accept business requests from the
customers mm-hmm yeah you end up with
asynchronous communication the the
general availability of the system is
higher it can tolerate it can still in
this example accept requests to create
orders even if part of the system is
temporarily unavailable I can see out
from this conversation when you talk
about one thing it's hard to completely
separate that from everything else and
while we're talking about communication
between microservices you're introducing
issues around transactionality and I do
want to now explicitly move on and talk
about transactionality and how it's
different in micro service application
you mentioned the saga pattern what what
problem does the saga pattern solve in
and how does it solve that so basically
the saga pattern is a way of
implementing transactions that span
services so within a service you have
you know traditional assuming you're
using a relational database you have
traditional passage transactions but
between databases it's sort of you could
say that using acid transactions in the
form of two-phase commit or XA has
fallen out of fashion for a variety of
reasons including that two-phase commit
is a form of synchronous communication
which as mentioned earlier you know
impacts the availability of your system
so the idea with sagas is that instead
of having a transaction that spans
multiple services of two-phase to to PC
transaction that spans multiple services
you break it down into a series of local
transactions what it in each one of the
services that contains data that needs
to be updated so in the Calif we simple
example that I
use is imagine like in order to create a
create an order you have to check and
reduce the customers available credit
you know magic is like there's a
business rule that says the customers
credit you know customer has a credit
limit that can never be violated so in
this example you need to create an order
and reduce the available credit so that
those up so those are updates that need
to be need to happen in both services
and so the way that's done with a sagar
is you could for instance you create an
order in one service in the order
service in the pending state that then
sends a message to the customer service
to reserve credit and then the customer
service sends back a message to the
order service saying that credit was
approved was was reserved or maybe there
was an insufficient credit and then the
order service can approve or reject that
order so so you've broken it down into a
set of steps that are local with
messaging as the coordination mechanism
between them and and so that's sort of
an event is essentially that is an
eventually consistent model for
transactions if we were in a model if I
could do some code and it might not look
exactly like this if you read the code
because you have all this propagation of
transactions through different layers
but we're still in the same process so I
could do begin transaction save the user
debit the credit insert the order insert
the charge information insert delivery
address and commit and it's yeah ferry
goes well it's all going to be saved
worse cases it wasn't saved but we don't
have this problem of we debited the
credit and we inserted the delivery
dress but no order was created it's at
least we can say it's all or nothing now
in the Micra service world you're
talking about these things being in
different services and somewhat fel some
might succeed and you're solving that
with the saw
pattern seems to me for this to work you
need to ensure that when you commit
something that you've committed the
message atomically along with the work
that each Micra service has done locally
and that you're sure that the message
will get delivered am I correct in going
that direction yeah it's it's funny we
like digging getting deeper into this
graph of problem problem solutions right
we've gone from the micro service
architecture to the database / service
pattern to the saga pattern and now
we're in this what kind of sub problem
area which I call transactional
messaging and it now interestingly so
yeah as you identified this each step of
the saga needs to do two things first it
needs to update the database create an
order or update the customers credit and
then it needs to send a message to say
that it's done that and ironically in a
traditional application you might use a
distributed transaction for that that
spanned the database and your message
broker but that's essentially the the
kind of technology that we're trying to
avoid and so in order to atomically
update the database and publish a
message there's two patterns that you
can use so one pattern is the
transactional outbox pattern so there's
this pattern as part of the asset
transaction that updates the database it
inserts a message into an outbox table
so that's just done atomically right and
then there's a second step that is
retrieving the message from their outbox
table and publishing it to the message
broker and that that will give you the
atomicity that you need along with the
and the guarantee that eventually that
message will be published to the message
broker the message broker is some
technology like Kafka or rabbitmq or
something that handles the delivery of
messages
between the services correct yeah
so the message broker needs to provide
certain guarantees and needs to give you
at least once delivery it also needs to
preserve guarantee will give you ordered
delivery
these sort of messes these messages or
events need to arrive in the order
within which they were published
otherwise things could get really
confusing and so there are certain and
there's another problem where you need
to somehow scale up consumers while also
guaranteeing delivery and so message
brokers that provide all three out of
the box include Kafka and ActiveMQ and
then to scale out the consumers with
other with a couple of other brokers it
was RabbitMQ and also Redis read a
stream specifically you know the open
source product that project that I work
on eventuate as you mentioned eventuate
dot IO we ended up building in it some
extra code on top of those message
brokers to enable scaling out consumers
properly digitalocean is the easiest
cloud platform to deploy manage and
scale applications of any size removing
infrastructure friction and providing
predictability so developers and their
teams can develop faster and focus on
building software that customers love
with thousands of in-depth tutorials and
an active community we provide the
support you need digitalocean stands out
of the crowd due to its simplicity high
performance and no billing surprises try
digitalocean for free at D o.co slash se
radio we have a show coming up on
messaging architectures which it doesn't
have a show number yet because asn't
been published but it will be published
by the time people are listening to this
and it will go into to some of these
issues in interest of time we won't by
any means to be able to cover even all
the major areas in your book but I
wanted to hit on some some thoughts
stuff that I thought was the most
interesting I wanted
to move on to another area which is
introduced near the beginning of
querying you introduce the pattern of
the API gateway what is that pattern and
what problem does it solve so the API
gateway is one of the communication
patterns in the area that is focused on
is the is what I call external API so in
other words what API does the
application exposed to the outside
which might be literally the outside
outside of the firewall or it could just
be other parts of the organization if I
have a hundred micro services they may
not all be public correct so the idea
with the API gateway is that it's
similar to the facade pattern in object
oriented design it defines the public
interface of your application so clients
talk to the API gateway and then it's
responsible for implementing
each say rest endpoint by invoking the
appropriate services it generally does
three things one it will world just
simply function as a reverse proxy so
routing routing each incoming request
like create an order it will route that
to the order service it can it will also
implement edge functions such as
security potentially other things like
rate limiting and so on and then it
might also implement API composition so
imagine that a client wants to know the
status of an order so that water status
could actually be scattered across
multiple services so the order service
would know some parts of the order
status the kitchen service would in in
the food to go application would know
about the status of the order at the
kitchen like when is it in the middle of
being prepared is it you know what's the
estimated ready for pickup time
and then the delivery service will know
about the estimated delivery time and
then perhaps if it's in the mitts it
actually if it's in the process of being
delivered where it is and then say the
accounting service would know other
things so it's like the status is
scattered across there in that example
for different services so rather than
the client making four different
requests it just success to the API
gateway give me the order status and
then the API gateway goes and makes
requests to each of those services
gathers back the four responses and
returns the response to the client and
that has two benefits one is the sort of
performance or efficiency aspect
particularly if it's like a mobile
device trying to making a request over a
low lower performance higher latency
mobile network but it also implements it
basically as encapsulating the the
internals of the of the architecture the
service so the clients are not aware of
the individual services which which is a
good thing because the architecture can
evolve I I think one of the things
you're talking about in this case is
issue you identify in the book by the
name chattiness yes going tomorrow what
would is chattiness so essentially there
ends up being a that's often a mismatch
in granularity between the data that
needs to that the client wants to render
on on a page or a screen and the
fine-grain nature or relatively fine
grained nature of your services so in
other words especially on the owner with
a desktop you want user experience do
you think about like the Amazon detail
product detail page it's displaying a
heck of a lot of information basic
product information delivery estimates
when you last ordered it perhaps whole
bunch of you know reviews two or three
different kinds of recommendations
seller ranking so on and so forth right
you could imagine that
each of those individual pieces of data
resides in a service and so one page can
easily correspond to potentially tens or
more services and so if the client had
to get each one of those pieces of data
individually that results in a lot of
round trips which for certain types of
clients especially mobile devices would
would be generally not a good idea right
it's potentially poor user experience
there's the risk of like you know
draining the battery faster and so on so
the idea is with a sip with the API
gateway pattern is that each client can
be given its own optimized API which in
some cases I mean applications I've
worked on it's almost like for each
screen there isn't there is a dedicated
API endpoint that so the client can just
so give me the data and it gets back a
blob you know relatively large blob of
data that's basically adjoined from or
composed by cooling multiple services
the monolith you would do a lot of this
integration in sequel where you'd hit an
endpoint and it would go and join a
bunch of tables together sounds like
what you're doing here is you're moving
that joining function into this API
gateway and you put the long-haul hop in
front of that and then it's going out in
the data center and doing super short
hops to pull all these chunks together
and merge them yeah that's essentially
right and so you know one place to do
that is in the API gateway or the API
gateway gateway routes to a service that
implements this composition another
issue you bring up is consistency which
you don't have in the monolith because
you're always doing commits and leaving
the database in a nice consistent state
do you have a problem where this API
gateway is going and hitting all these
services and it gets back
things that don't all quite make sense
together because they reflect things
that are in different states of
convergence toward a consistency yeah
so essentially yeah in a monolith you
retrieve data you're most likely going
to do that within a transaction that
will give you a transactional e
consistent view of the data whereas in a
micro service architecture with API
composition multiple transactions of you
know one in each service of being
executed and so you theoretically could
get sort of an inconsistent view of the
data is there a solution to that or is
that trade-off that you need to make to
get these other benefits I mean
fundamentally that that's a consequence
of having split the system up and in the
way that you have chosen to split it up
I mean one of the interesting things is
say but for a given set of requirements
there are potentially multiple different
ways of decomposing the system so for
instance you know in this class I teach
this three-day clasp where the salt with
the where students come up with a micro
service architecture for given a set of
requirements I think that you know
typically the class will come up with
three or four different architectures
and each one represents the sort of
different set of trade-offs in the sense
that some queries might correspond to a
single service but other queries chorus
pot will require gathering data from
multiple services and then that's an
architecture a in version B it's
different it's divided up differently
and which impacts different queries and
and so so essentially if you find that
because of the way that you've divided
up your system into services it results
in a query that gives you up
unacceptable inconsistencies you you
might actually have to go back and
revisit your decomposition and adjust
the service boundaries so that you you
have the consistency that you need we
did a show a little while back about the
post Grey's sequel query planner one of
the takeaways from that show is the
query planner is brilliant at costing
out different ways of getting
information and doing something that's
pretty smart to get you all the
information you want and if you didn't
have that you'd be looking at okay I'll
grab all the users and then I'll go out
and get all these addresses one at a
time and you probably would do a worse
job in the query planner are we taking a
step backwards here when we decompose
and and now we are test telling our
developers to become as essentially a
sequel query optimizer but maybe they're
not as good at it as the one in Postgres
I see the analogy though right in the
sense that I think basically it sounds
like you just write some giant sequel
query hand it over to the query planner
and it figures it out as opposed to
breaking it up I wouldn't say it's
exactly the same problem but there's a
certain kind of there are some analogies
here in the sense that essentially
things like transaction management joins
reference maintaining referential
integrity ends up being moved from the
database where it's just all automatic
and you don't think too hard about it up
to the application level so if you're
using the saga patent you some aspects
of what you're doing are more
complicated and then querying is more
complicated and then say ref foreign key
constraints you're now having to enforce
those at the application level so like
when you create an order and it's got a
customer ID
that that's in the order service and you
can't have a foreign key constraint to
the customer table anymore so there's a
bunch of stuff that you have to do at
the application level which makes things
harder right but on the other hand the
assumption is that there are benefits to
splitting up right and and hopefully the
that the benefits outweigh the drawbacks
so as it you know for instance if you're
working on a service hopefully the focus
of your attention is on implementing say
the complex business logic within the
service and the sort of the the
complicated stuff around sagas and quit
and querying a relatively small part of
what you have to worry about even though
like my whole book is you could say it's
on all this complicated stuff but it's
just that the idea hopefully the
complicated stuff is sort of on the
periphery of your services and the the
the meaty stuff that's implementing the
business logic is actually the bulk of
what you're having to do fair enough I
want to move on it in ensure we cover as
much as we can one of the areas which is
in my experience extraordinarily more
complicated when you go to micro
services is testing what are the major
differences in testing and I'll say
we've had a ton of shows on testing
almost all about testing program logic
what are the main differences from
single program testing to micro service
testing testing and a micro service
architecture is simultaneously I would
argue easier and it's harder so it's
easier in the sense that a service is a
relatively small
amount of code and and so writing
automated tests for it are a lot simpler
and there are the simpler and faster
running than they would be if you had
some monstrous monolithic application so
there is this notion that testability is
enhanced by the microservice
architecture the complication comes from
the fact that services don't often often
don't exist in isolation right let's
just say the order service is having to
collaborate with the customer service so
there's a there's a coupling there see
the order service is dependent upon the
api of the customer service whether that
API is is literally a REST API or
perhaps it's some it's an asynchronous
kind of API there's still a dependency
there and so there's sort of a bunch of
problems around that like well I want to
test my order service but it depends on
the customer service and then let's
shall we say the customer service might
depend on three other services and
suddenly you've got this whole tree of
transitive dependencies just because you
want to test one service and that could
actually get quite complicated quite
quickly because you're having but in
theory you're having the provision all
of these services so one one at one
important trick there is is to tech you
want a way to test services in isolation
while being confident that when you put
them together they can actually
communicate successfully so there's a
there's a few different patterns there
and one key idea is consumer driven
contract testing where the interaction
between
Atkins well consumer a client and a
service is captured by a set of
contracts which are basically in the
case of HTTP example request response
has so it's like specification by
example and those those examples or
contracts are used to test both the
service and the consumer in isolation
and provides so if you're testing both
with the same contracts then in theory
fingers cross when you put them together
they can communicate and then the other
part of it is there's component testing
for services which is where you test a
service in isolation but but you use
test doubles for any of its dependencies
so the order service for instance would
be tested in isolation with a test
double for the customer service and the
test double would if it was HTTP would
be programmed to reply with canned HTTP
responses for a given you know when it
gets a request or if it's they're
communicating via a message broker would
be sent back and reply pre-canned reply
messages so there's a bunch of these
newer testing techniques that you have
to use but the whole the end result is
you're able to test services in
isolation while being confident that
when you deploy them they will actually
communicate this sounds very much like
the use of mocking which I'm familiar
with in Java or groovy you have a
library which will instantiate a runtime
a class that implements an interface but
you can script out what you want that
the methods on that class to do when you
call them just for that test and that
could include returning a certain result
or raising an exception so you
abstractly that concept and moved it out
to the HTTP server rather than the
programming language is that correct
yeah yeah so it's like what you're
describing like with mock objects like
say with a Makita framework in Java
that's a particular form of test double
but you can have other forms such as a
fake HTTP server and then for instance
there's the wire mock project that was
an open-source project it's basically
why a mock Esaias mojito for HTTP so
that that that's pretty pretty useful
and there's other ones like that as well
and then you can do the same thing with
messaging as well so if you've got
services that are communicating for our
message broker it's pretty
straightforward to have a test double
that when it sees when it receives
message X it sends back message Y when
not you're talking about using these
contracts my first thought was I am
going to implement an HTTP endpoint and
I think the variable in a JSON document
has one name but the client has a
different idea of what the name of that
field is I think you've solved that by
forcing both ends of the endpoint to use
the same contract and that should detect
a lot of bugs that you might find at
compile time if you are compiling your
whole thing into one big monolith yeah I
mean it it's very true that especially
when you're using a statically typed
language like Java any any interface
mismatches manifest themselves as
compile time errors which is really good
right but in a distributed system you
don't have that kind of guarantee
especially over the other the other key
point is your system is not static
services are constantly being updated
and so preventing api's from
accidentally being made like well
introducing breaking changes
accidentally in your API is it's really
critical that you prevent that from
happening and so consumer-driven
contract testing is is a is does exactly
that it prevents that the service team
from accidentally changing the API in a
way that would break any of that that
the consumers we did a show a little
while ago about Jenkins we had some
fairly general discussions about the
concept of a pipeline Jenkins can
execute any kind of pipeline you have
some views in your book about what the
deployment pipeline would look like in a
micro service architecture talk about
that what is the pipeline that you
recommend so so in general I mean a
deployment pipeline is essentially a
series of automated test Suites and the
idea is as you go from left to right the
test Suites potentially get get slower
and while more sophisticated and slower
but get more production like so maybe
the first stage of your your deployment
pipeline might just execute unit tests
so they they execute blindingly fast but
but essentially don't catch a whole
class of errors and so then you have the
next phase execute some more more
sophisticated yet more expensive kinds
of tests and so a lot of key idea there
is that yeah you can go implement the
deployment pipeline using pick your
favorite CI server or cloud or cloud
provider it doesn't really matter too
much which one you do but you know
important idea is that essentially each
service has its own deployment pipeline
so it's being built and tested
independently of all of the other
services and then oh I suppose I should
say they are ideally the final stage of
the deployment pipeline actually pushes
that service into production I mean in
theory it could all all of these
different spur service deployment
pipelines could feed into some kind of
end
when testing environment like what you
would commonly call a staging
environment but you know there's a lot
of thinking around that is that instead
of having a staging environment which is
only a rough approximation of production
and also the fact that end-to-end tests
tend to be kind of slow and kind of
brittle practice it can be much more
effective to just deploy into production
in a very disciplined way using like
canary deployments or Bluegreen
deployments and with careful monitoring
so that if there are problems you can
quickly roll back moving on another area
you provide patterns is production izing
or production readiness how do you
define production readiness well this
all this what should we say you know
there's one keep absolutely key part of
what a service does is implement is is
the business logic right I mean that
that's like the whole reason for it
existing but then in order to be sort of
deployable in a real application there's
a whole bunch of other stuff that you
have to deal with for instance security
it's the a really critical thing right
is services need to be secure so that's
one part of being production ready
that's separate from the business logic
and then another big part that apart
there is observability you know in a
sense well you always have to deal with
sort of observability or monitor ability
even side a monolith except that it's a
bit more complex in a micro service
architecture because when requests come
in they can bounce around between
services and so troubleshooting and and
like figuring out where the latency is
is being you know as high is much more
complex in a monolith I suppose you just
pray run a profile or of some kind and
you can track it down but if requests
are bought bouncing around between a
whole bunch of services
it's not so obvious and so there's a
whole bunch of observability patterns
that you have to implement ranging from
simple ones like having a health check
and point that the runtime environment
can periodically ping like make of get
rich TTP get request to to verify that
your service instance is healthy and is
written can handle production traffic
there's a you know another pattern is
log aggregation so the logs from all of
the services are being sucked up into a
log aggregator where they're stored and
they can be searched
another critical pattern is distributed
tracing so you know each inbound request
gets a request ID or trace ideas is
cooled that gets propagated from one
service to the next ends up in log
messages and then that interacts nicely
with log aggregation because then you
can search for that request ID and see
all of the relevant logs plus the
services report what they're doing to a
distributed tracing server like open
Zipkin which can then display traces and
you can get the time breakdown for a
sample request you can see where the
latency is being spent you know is
occurring and so on and then there's
other patterns like application metrics
by gathering metrics at the app board
that sort of business level metrics
about what your services are doing and
then feeding them into a metrics
database where they can be aggregated
visualized and alerted one that you
didn't mention I was going to ask you
about is the externalized configuration
pattern oh yeah talk about that one so
the basic idea with that which is which
is really one that that's you you'd have
to deal with in a monolithic application
as well is the application should just
be built once I by the first stage of
the deployment pipeline and then you can
run
in multiple environments but what that
means is that say the configuration
properties of external services like the
database server can't be hardwired into
the source code because they're
different in each environment and so
they need to be passed in at runtime
somehow and so you need an external ice
configuration mechanism for doing that
which might be something as simple as
setting environment variables that works
quite nicely in a docker environment
where it's easy to whether you like say
if you're using kubernetes right you
have a config map that defines some some
property values that then get injected
into the container as environment
variables and then like if you're using
spring boots spring boot will just pick
them up and make them available in sight
the spring application context but
there's other mechanisms that you can
use while config files that get injected
in or you can have so those are sort of
the push model or there's the pull model
where the service can go and request the
its configuration from a config server
let's say you've got a couple of
different options there what all these
things were ties them together that
we've been discussing this last few
minutes is enable you to manage
understand and troubleshoot the
application when you run it in the
production environment is that a fair
summary yeah well yeah like yeah I
suppose manage as in like yeah configure
it and figure out what the heck is doing
okay we're getting pretty close to the
end of our time I had section of
questions about anti-patterns
maybe I'll ask you what is one of the
most pernicious or most common anti
patterns that you observe well I would
say this - I mean so one is technical
which is where you
you create an architecture where you
have a set of services that are
communicating via HTTP and and perhaps
with this with the assumption that
networking is free so you've taken a
monolithic design modularized it and
then given each modular REST API so they
you're likely to have performance
problems because there's lots of network
round trips so latency will be horrible
also you've basically built a tightly
coupled system with single points of
well multiple points of failure and then
if you've really done it a bad job of
modularization you basically end up with
building a distributed monolith where
changes to one service just ripple
throughout the the sort of all the chain
of dependencies and you end up having to
make multiple changes to multiple
services in lockstep so you've basically
got a monolith that's made of services
which is like the West best of the worst
of both worlds
so there's sort of technical anti
patterns like that but then but then
maybe the more challenging ones a more
sort of organizational political process
policy oriented which I gave it a
keynote gave this talk pot hot pot holes
in the road from monolithic hell a
conference and that you know an example
of those one if one of them is called
the red flag law and then its name comes
from the fact that when automobiles or
self-driving vehicles first came out in
sort of the early 19th century that some
jurisdictions passed the law where a
pedestrian had to walk in front of the
car holding a red flag so you kind of
had which is presumably that the vehicle
could actually go faster than the
pedestrian right but but you slowed it
down because of the law and I've seen
this in sites I Morgan
where it's like yeah we're gonna have
microservices but then they don't change
their policies or their processes right
so for instance they might just stick
with manual testing I automated like
many organizations one of the biggest
weaknesses is actually the lack of
automated testing so you've got this
architecture that gives you the
potential to deliver software really
quickly but then you basically have
someone walking in front of it with a
red flag but because you've got manual
testing or maybe you've got policies
that say no deployments during business
hours and you can only deploy on the
fourth Saturday of each month at
midnight so it's sort of like you know
and it's in a sense you're missing the
point of the micro service architecture
and you're not going to properly benefit
from it thank you for that and we're
getting pretty close to the end to wrap
up we mentioned your company eventuate
dot IO Microsoft I know which has many
patterns your book working listeners
find your book oh yeah so if you got a
Microsoft says dot io / book you will
find a description of the book and and
links to where you can buy it you have
any upcoming conference talks that
listeners might want to attend and in
September I will you know the full
conference season of beat feel some
conference or the other okay Chris thank
you very much for speaking to software
engineering radio great thank you
this has been Robert blumen thank you
for listening thanks for listening the
se radio an educational program brought
to you by Triple E software magazine for
more about the podcast including other
episodes visit our website at se - radio
net
to provide feedback you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or through
our slack channel at SC radio.com you
can also email us a team at SC - radio
net this and all other episodes of SU
radio is licensed under Creative Commons
license 2.5 thanks for listening